Guide to the Michi Kobi Papers TAM.697
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Michi Kobi Papers
1977-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kobi, Michi
Nakamura, Maggie
TAM.697
5.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 flat box, 1 media box, and 1 oversize folder.
18 audiocassettes
Michi Kobi (1924-2016) was a Japanese American actress and activist who was forcibly removed from her home and incarcerated at the Central Utah Relocation Center, a concentration camp (euphemistically referred to as an internment camp) in Topaz, Utah during World War II. The Michi Kobi Papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and drafts of her writings. Correspondence predominantly relates to Kobi's study of Japanese American history and the incarceration of Japanese Americans, and includes letters to personal friends, scholars, and activists in the Japanese American community. Kobi's writings include multiple drafts of an untitled novel about Japanese Americans in San Francisco, research files on Japanese Americans, and drafts of her unpublished memoir about her experience at the Topaz concentration camp. The collection also contains photographs from Kobi's visit to the Topaz historic site in the 1980s, as well as audio recordings of conferences and meetings on this period of Japanese American incarceration.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Margaret S. (Maggie) Nakamura in 2016. The accession number associated with these gifts are 2016.061 and 2017.003.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Michi Kobi (1924-2016), born Machiko Okamoto, was a Japanese American actress and activist. During World War II, she, along with 110,000 other Nisei, was forcibly removed from her home and incarcerated at the Central Utah Relocation Center, a concentration camp (euphemistically referred to as an internment camp) in Topaz, Utah. She turned to acting while incarcerated and after the war pursued an acting career in New York, appearing in film and Broadway productions. Kobi also worked to draw attention to the injustices of Japanese American incarceration, and in 1980 served as the co-chair of the East Coast Japanese Americans for Redress. The organization advised the federal Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians and helped organize the November 1981 commission hearings in New York City, which concluded that the incarceration was a grave injustice based on racial prejudice and not justified by military necessity. The Commission recommended an official Government apology and narrowly defined redress payments to survivors, which were introduced into legislation as the Civil Liberties Act of 1988.
Scope and Contents
The Michi Kobi Papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings, subject files, and drafts of her writings. Correspondence includes personal friends, scholars, and activists in the Japanese American community predominantly focused on Kobi's study of Japanese American history and the incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II. The bulk of this collection documents Kobi's involvement in the campaign for Reconciliation and Redress for Japanese Americans forcibly removed from their homes and incarcerated during WWII. Materials include Kobi's original writings about the experiences of Japanese Americans in these concentration camps, research files on US policy toward Asian Americans, papers and programs from Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) conferences, audio recordings of meetings and conferences, and notes from public events focused on the redress movement. Kobi's writings include multiple drafts of an untitled novel about Japanese Americans in San Francisco, research files on Japanese Americans, and drafts of her unpublished memoir alternately titled "Utah Pilgrimage" or "Going back to Topaz." The collection also contains photographs from Kobi's 1981 visit to the historic site of Central Utah Relocation Center, the concentration camp (euphemistically referred to as an internment camp) in Topaz, Utah where Kobi was incarcerated. This collection also includes an oral history recording of the Togasaki family.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Japanese Americans -- Civil rights; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Correspondence.; Memoirs; Japanese Americans -- Reparations.; Topaz (Utah); Concentration camps -- United States; Nakamura, Maggie; Central Utah Relocation Center
- Correspondence Files, 1988-2015 (Box 1)
- Subject Files: Nisei and Japanese American Issues, 1987-2014 (Box 1)
- Utah Pilgrimage: Draft of Memoir, 1983, 1986 (Box 1, Box 2)
- Novel Manuscript, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Box 2)
- Going Back to Topaz: Draft of Memoir, 1977-1992 (Box 2)
- Subject Files: Japanese American Culture and Religion, 1982-2012 (Box 3)
- Subject Files: United States Policy toward Asian Americans, 1987-2015 (Box 3)
- Redress Movement, 1981-1988 (Box 4)
- Subject Files: Incarceration of Japanese Americans During WWII, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Box 5)
- Novel Notes and Manuscripts, 1983-2001 (Box 5)
- Topaz: Articles and Memorabilia, 1983-2012 (Box 5)
- Utah Pilgrimage: Draft of Memoir, 1985 (Box 5)
- Topaz Demolition Site Photographs, 1980s (Box 6, Box Tamiment Shared OS009, Folder 1)